good morning everyone
in our today's session we will be
focusing on proximal lesions of the
posterior teeth and
we shall learn
how to perform aesthetic restorations in
these clinical manifestations of curious
lesions
using dental composites
despite significant improvements in
composite systems and adhesive systems
since their
introduction posterior restorations
still require a careful placement
technique in order to avoid
micro leakage
post-operative sensitivity or less than
ideal anatomy
marginal adaptation and micro leakage
prevention is
most critical at the gingival margin
which is determined by the accident of
lesion itself
the formation of an adequate contact
during the insertion of class 2 raisin
composite
can be particularly challenging as the
lesion extends more gingivally
in more superficial lesions such as this
one
it's comparatively easier to manage
because of its relationship with the
incidental tissues
size of the lesion is directly related
to the prognosis as
a matrix adaptation is easier which can
securely engage and provide optimum seal
at the gingival floor
as the lesion size increased and as it
extends more gingivally
the more challenging the situation is
as the preparation is enlarged
resistance form as well as bonding
variables must be kept in mind during
preparation metricing and restoration
because
whenever there is some kind of root
involvement there will be some bonding
issues because of
less mineral content maybe we are trying
to bond on a cementum
and the root dentine already has very
less mineral content and higher collagen
content so that's why there will be some
bonding issues
uh next we'll there will be some
isolation problems because whenever
there is a class two lesion depending on
the size there are some inflamed papilla
incidentally
and
these inflamed papilla
uh produce exuded the inflammatory exit
which can interfere with the etched or
newly prepared surface
another variable is the depth of light
penetration in these regions if
the depth is greater there will be
lesser chances of a proper light
penetration and hence there will be less
degree of conversion
and because of less degree of conversion
there could be some
uh problems with the bonding or there
could be some uncured composite there
are chances of secondary lesion as well
as post treatment hygiene maintenance
problems because there are chances of
overhanging in this region as well
to build up the proximal wall and the
insertion of class 2 composite
restoration requires proper meta rising
for a good contact formation hence
correct use of enamel and dentine
etching bonding steps
and
incremental placement of the raisin
composites
and careful finishing is extremely
important
anatomically correct and tight contacts
are difficult to achieve with resin
restorations because
resin composite materials are not
condensable
like amalgam
the use of amalgam matrix bands like
flatmate
for composite restorations
generally leads to a straight point
contact that are located in the occlusal
third of
uh the tooth which leads to under
contouring of the situation as you can
see in this illustration if i'm using a
flat matrix it is it is not going to
create a contoured proximal contact
so
hence we are getting a flat contact
which is not ideal uh remaining under
contoured restoration will lead to
overstimulation of the tissues
the matrix systems for composite
materials are designed to create curved
proximal surfaces
and tight contact areas
these are generally comprised of thin
contoured matrix bands and a tooth
separator
you can see that it is creating optimum
contours in the proximal contact area
so after restoration
it is producing an anatomical contact
which is an ideal contact
talking about the indications
these are almost the same indications
whenever doing a composite restoration
in the posterior region
again small and moderate restorations
preferably within enamel margin is
advised
most premolars in molar restorations
particularly when the aesthetics is in
high demand
a restoration that does not provide all
the occlusal contacts
is generally weaker
and
a restoration that does not have a
higher occlusal contact or the patient
is
not suffering from any para functional
habits
a restoration that can appropriately
isolate during the procedure if you
cannot perform adequate isolation there
is a very bad prognosis of these kind of
restorations
uh some restorations that may serve as
foundations for crowns and some very
large restorations that are used to
strengthen the remaining or weakened
structure
when the operating site
cannot be appropriately isolated i told
you that these are among the
contraindication because if you will do
the restoration
there will be minimal um
curing in the gingival region there are
chances of bond failure in that region
so it's always contraindicated that you
use some other materials such as you can
try
a sandwich technique by using resin
modified in these areas prior to use
any composite
uh whenever there are some high occlusal
forces because of pair functional habits
this is among the contra indications
uh patients who are having high carry
susceptibility and the patients who are
with poor oral hygiene the composites
are contraindicated in these situations
so again whenever we are talking about
the advantages
uh aesthetics is the number one
advantage followed by um we are not
removing a lot of tooth structure as we
are trying to do in amalgam which
requires
a strict geometry in order to get ideal
retention and resistance form
and
with composites it is easier and less
complex with preparation and since we
are using
bonding system
it is providing insulation and the
composite itself is an insulating
material
there is a decreased chance of micro
leakage because of use of bonding
adhesive system
and we are also reinforcing remaining
tooth structure by using composite and
adhesive dentistry
among the disadvantages if
not used carefully uh there will be some
polymerization shrinkage effects some
post op sensitivity or debonding if
you have not
followed all the recommendations during
the preparation and etching and bonding
process
with some materials there is a low
fracture toughness and
it is quite a technique sensitive and
time-consuming as compared to amalgam
and
it is also expensive than amalgam so
these are among the disadvantages
so the problems with composites for use
in class 2 restoration is number one
it's difficult to it's not impossible
but it is difficult to achieve moisture
control
but if you are using rubber dam you
don't have to worry about that
and in deep sub-gingival extension areas
uh adaptation
of
the matrix band and deep margin
elevation and these are all difficult
procedures to attempt for
so
next we'll discuss the clinical
techniques
for class 2 composite restorations
as you know
the shade of the tooth is the most
important
parameter when aesthetics is a paramount
the shade of the tooth should be
determined before the teeth are
subjected to any prolonged drying
because dehydrated teeth become lighter
in shade as a result of decrease in
translucency
minor or no tooth preparation
it may be necessary to clean the
operating site with a slurry of pumice
to remove the plaque pellicle and
superficial stains along with the
calculus deposits if there are
knowing the pre-op occlusal
relationship is paramount for optimum
restoration
so we shall mark the
occlusal marks before any restorations
local anesthesia should be provided
to make more pleasant and uninterrupted
procedure
it also resulted in marked
reduction in salivation
isolation is extremely important for a
successful composite restoration
although with cotton rolls and other
means of indirect isolation
composite restoration can be performed
but it's
highly unpredictable
in this pictorial you guys can see this
wedge application in the teeth
each matrix band should be secured with
a wedge
a wedge is needed to maintain adaptation
of the matrix to the tooth
and the gingival margin to avoid the
overhangs and prevent adjacent tooth
from getting nicked with high speed
handpiece
excessive wedging forces are unnecessary
when an additional two separators such
as rings will be used
so inserted wedge where the embroidery
is wide from buckle to lingual or from
lingual to buckle
coming towards the benefits of the
wedging
are the pre-wedging will cause slight
separation incidentally
it depresses the interdental papillae
it controls hemorrhage
prevent oozing of gravicular fluid
it seals the matrix gingivally and it
also ensures the tight contacts
think before drill
so we'll coming towards
the tooth preparation
wedging of the proximal contacts
to
prevent the adjacent tooth
and to prevent the overhangs and the
restorations
creating access to the faulty structure
with your high speed handpiece
removal of the faulty structure
convenience form for the restoration
and then the retention is obtained by
the bonding
tooth preparation
for class 2 has decreased pulpal depth
of axial walls which allows greater
conservation of tooth structure
a closer and proximal wall converge
occlusally and provide additional
retention form
from the vertical movements
proximal box preparation has a cable
surface angle at right angle to the
enamel surface
facially or lingually
bevels are given on the occlusal surface
and that are optimal
due to the letter optional due to the
direction of enamel rods whereas
proximal surface beveling must be done
prudently
gingival floors
should clear the contact apically and
they should be butt joint
after the tooth cavity preparation the
metric system is selected
based on the operator preference the
cavity location and the size
if the contact is not opened during the
tooth preparation
then conventional matrices materials may
be simpler to use rather than the curved
matrix bands and the separating rings
if you are using a toefl my retainer
then always pre-burnish your band using
a ball ended burnisher to create a
slight contour at the contact point
otherwise it will create a flat contact
which is under contoured again and not
ideal
in larger cavities
a circumferential band can be chosen
over sectional bands
ultra thin curved
or self-retaining circumferential bands
enhance the ability to form tight curved
contacts areas
and should be used rather than the
traditional circumferential amalgam
matrix bands and a toefl my retenders
if the tooth is in irregular position
and number ear shapes can sometimes
prevent seating of the ring
it is useful for a dentist to have a
variety of separating rings with
different
tine shapes
with round or rectangular cross sections
for a better fit in some buckle or
lingual embryos
when a metric system and a separating
ring is used the metric
position should be verified prior to the
application of the morning agent and
resin composite material
a properly matrix tooth should no gap
shows no gap along the gingival margin
between the tooth and the matrix band
the
problems with the matrix
use always pre-controlled metrics to
form a proper contact point
if you use a
straight matrix it will also make a flat
surface and it will retain it
like under contoured restoration
your metric should be passively and
shouldn't deformed
if the matrix is deformed again the
restoration will be deformed because
you're going to pack in the restoration
when it's been maturized
always remember your matrix retainer
tines should be inserted
below matrix and the wedge to hold
the tooth from the transitional line
angles or the spots
let's discuss some clinical aspects of
class 2 restorations
class 2 is a challenge why it is a
challenge the reason being is
what i feel in my whole clinical
practice
that to find an actual tooth is a
problem
patient complains that food is trapped
but most of the times when you examine
that situation clinically
the ridge remains intact
so to find a real culprit is a problem
for the dentist for that you have to
evaluate class to cavity in five
different aspects
but before examination you have to ask
the patients to have some scaling in the
polishing as you know that poor oral
hygiene is a leading cause of the class
2 cavity
so with lot of calculus and the plaque
you cannot examine you can miss some
details during examinations so after
scaling and the polishing what five
factors you have to evaluate
see any redness and inflammation around
that area
that indicates there is some food trap
areas there so it leads to inflammation
of the gums
see any roughness of the tooth surface
that is only possible if you dry the
tooth and the surrounding tissues
do floss to evaluate the contact points
then the next thing is evaluate if there
is any discolorations like in that
picture there is a visible
discolorations on the measles aspect of
the molar but the bridge is 100 is
perfectly fine so you have to evaluate
all these things in the final you have
to go with the bitewing radiograph that
is the recommended radiograph for the
class 2 inspection
so as i told you that in previous slide
there is a black discoloration on the
occlusal aspect so when you open the
cavity there is a visible carious
lesions so you need magnifications and
you need proper evaluations with drying
of the soft tissues and dental heart
structures
what is an ideal contact as we know that
in posterior teeth the contact is on the
buccal sides and at the junction of the
occlusal and the middle third
but here
the contact between two premolars
is good and but the contact between
premolar and the molar is full of
defects the ridge is intact but there's
a lingual carious lesions for that
because that area was just filled with
some plug so when you ask the patient go
for scaling and the polishing then that
area visible to you so you have to
follow the protocols
like that one that's a very clear
picture there's open contact and the
food trap is visible there when there is
food lodgement there is
demineralizations and that
demineralizations
leads to
demonization of the dentine and then
enamel gets unspotted and then fractured
with mastications
which is recommended but for class 2
cavity preparations that's a round bar
round diamond and round carbide but
remember that when you prepare the
occlusal surface always use a small
round bar with a high speed handpiece
but when you go deep close to the pearl
when there is a chance of pulp exposure
always use a small round but
in slow speed handpiece with air water
spray and if you feel that the tails are
compromised you cannot evaluate a d part
of the cavity stop the water coolant use
only air coolant so that the main
purpose is just to cool the denting and
avoid overheating of the denting
what is the best way to isolate in a
class 2 cavity the picture that's
visible here it's androgyny cavity it's
occlusal cavity for that you can isolate
a single tooth but for the class 2 you
have to isol isolate multiple teeth so
that you can work freely because if you
isolate a single tooth you cannot
make a cavity or in proximal sides and
you can adapt the matrix so best way is
to have multiple teeth isolations and
the clamp that is good for the
restorative dentistry is wingless clamp
because it's small in size and it gives
you a space for better performance of
your dental work
as you see that when there's a one wall
missing it's an ideal cavity it's easier
to restore because you have the
neighboring premolar is there that
guides you about the height of the
marginal reach and helps you in the
adaptation of the matrix in a better way
so it's the easiest one but these are
very
rare in clinical practice because when
there is a class two cavity on one side
possibility there is a cavity on the
side as well
like that one when two teeth need to be
filled uh it means that to a different
teeth different walls are involved so
you can pass the matrix at the same time
and with the wedge at the same time and
build them at the same time no problem
in that
but here is a challenge here's a problem
because two adjacent walls are missing
you don't have
any guidance from height of the marginal
reach so here is a problem here you have
to build one wall at one time
so the wall that you have is stored it
guides you in building up of the second
wall and here you have to pass the two
metrics the same time but build one wall
at a time remove the matrix and then
shift your retainer to the next wall so
it gives you a tight contact but if you
try to build both walls at the same time
what would happen
there might be a space in between the
two two teeth that leads to poor contact
and then there's the same complaint of
the patient again and again the food
lodgement so try to understand you have
to build one wall at a time when you
when you have a cavity
in the adjacent teeth
the most important thing in class two is
to close the cervical contact
that's the most important thing because
when the contact is open there is a
problem with inflammation secondary
carries and then there is a contact is
open it leads to
marginal leakage as well so to close the
cervical contact you need a tight wedge
tight wedge and it might it should be a
wooden wedge it should not be a plastic
fish because it can slip away and if you
don't get a tight cervical contact you
can use a bigger edge or tie a teflon
tape on the wedge to make the contact
tight
a lot of colleagues ask me can we build
the proximal wall with the flowable
composite the answer is no the reason
being is flowable is a very soft
material it has poor strength so it can
fracture you need a packable composite
here in building of the proximal wall
because packable has more filler content
it is stronger as compared to the
flowable ones
so let's see a clinical case of class 2
composite restorations
a 30 year old female patient presented
to me with history of food trap between
upper first molar and second premolar
the tooth are almost covered with
calculus so before any examination
i advise the patient to go for scaling
as we know that
patient most of the times
they argue that they are only visiting
you for the restorations and they don't
need any scaling
but to evaluate a lesion
in an area with a lot of calculus
difficult for the dentist
so please always ask
so after examination the next step is to
prepare the cavity for cavity
preparation the most important thing is
you have to pass the interproximal wedge
because interproximal wedge helps you
in protection of the soft tissues and
also prevents the drilling of the
adjacent tooth and remember that the
wedge the good wedge is wooden and it
should be triangular and you have to
pass the vest from the buccal side to
the lingual side depending on the space
available in the embrasure area
so
next thing is you have to open up the
cavity i asked you already that you you
can use round diameter on the occlusal
surface
with the high speed hand piece when you
go down
use a round diamond but in slow speed
hand piece and try to use air and water
coolants but if your details are
compromised you can use an air coolant
as well here you can see that cavity is
still dirty is lot of demineralizations
and you cannot bond the composite in
that cavity the reason being is the
collagen is denatured and there's a
demonization so the composite cannot
bond perfectly so you have to remove all
of the carries
the next thing is uh i passed the rubber
dam why you know
why i not use a rubber dam in my
previous slides the reason being is
the contact was quite irregular so when
you try to pass the rubber dam in
irregular contacts rubber damp sheets
can be tear off so better to prepare the
cavity open up the proximal contacts and
then pass the rubber dam
so here the cavity is still dirty and
there's lot of a soft carries there we
have to remove it we have we don't have
to leave any carries there because that
carries is a weak part of the tooth that
can lead to debonding of the composites
so here you can see the cavity is very
clean there is no demonization left
there there is no dark carries enamel is
sound dentin is sound that's an ideal
cavity to restore with the composites
and always remember that the contact
should be opened between premolar and
the motor for the passive placement of
the matrix because the wall of the shape
of the wall of the proximal side is
always dependent on the shape of the
matrix but when the matrix is deformed
then the shape would be deformed so you
have to place a passive matrix and the
shape of the matrix should be preserved
so
next we just pass the two metrics
simultaneously and enter proximal wedge
in between and we will build one wall at
one time and as you see in the picture
the times of the matrix retainer should
be in between the matrix and the wedge
so we will fill one wall and then we
will remove the matrix from that wall
and shift the matrix retainer to the
next next tooth
so here
one wall is constructed no the matrix
lines have been shifted to the molar and
always remember that
you cannot build a two wall
simultaneously the reason being is i
told you already that the thickness of
the matrix can lead to the gap in
between the two molars so one wall at
one time and remove the matrix and shift
the times the next one
so here uh the class two has been
converted into class one so now we have
to restore the central part now
so the base of the cavity should be
filled with the flowable
around about one mm increments and then
remaining part of the box should be
filled with two millimeter increments
the packable packable composites and we
just did the cruiser part uh cusp bikers
so the occlusion of the patients them is
a priority for a dentist it should be
preserved a crucial part should not end
into a flat restorations that can create
a problem
in mastication
so here is a post-op situation
uh the very well adapted composites the
contacts are the tight and there is no
carious lesions visible so that's an
ideal contact that helps the patient
domestications and then there would be
no
food trap in between the molars
so that's
so after doing uh clinical work uh the
next thing is to evaluate your work with
some radiograph
that radiograph helps you to evaluate
your proximal contacts
and cycle part of the restoration that
remains open in most of clinical
situations when you don't adapt the
matrix well so that radiograph helps you
to evaluate
the performance of your
restorations
so guys
at the end of the lecture i want to
recommend you few things
and bitewing is a recommended radiograph
for class 2. you cannot take a
periapical radiograph to evaluate the
carious lesions
as we know that
periapical is only good for peripheral
area it don't tell you details about the
carious lesions and the extent of the
restorations so bitewing is a
recommended one
and the second thing is use a round
diamond and round carbide for the cavity
preparations i told you already that
when you try to open the occlusal cavity
in the crucial surface you use a round
diamond in a high speed hand piece but
when you go near to the bulb always work
in a very precise way need a round
diamond but in slow speed hand piece and
always drill the cavity in a brushing
actions don't drill drill drill okay and
then important thing is that you always
prepare a cavity with air and water
spray but if you cannot visualize the
details so you can just close the water
coolants and just work with the air
coolant so next thing is don't prepare
cavity without a wedge that's very
important thing because interproximal
wedge not only protects your soft
tissues but also protects the
neighboring tooth during cavity
preparations because most of time what
happens when you don't use a wedge you
can drill the adjacent
well adapted tooth
that once once there is a drilling so
there is a process of demineralization
starts so you have to avoid this thing
and the wear should be wooden it should
be triangular it should be tight enough
but if the wedge is not tight you can
wrap wrap up the wedge with some teflon
tape then the most important thing is
always use a pre-contoured matrix for
class 2 restorations because shape of
the matrix resembles the shape of the
proximal wall don't use a toefl mat
because always ends in a flat
restorations
and finally guys nothing is a challenge
until you work work work and you have to
work for the rest of your life
thank you guys